Guide to the Gail and Stephen Rudin atomic bomb collection, 1914-2009.
Rudin, Gail and Stephen Rudin atomic bomb collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gail and Stephen Rudin atomic bomb collection, 1914-2009.
6990
Rudin, Stephen,
.5 cubic feet.
Correspondence, printed materials, models, publications, photographs
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Letters, documents, photographs, drawings, and models (signed by Paul Tibbets) related to the atomic bomb and its use in Hiroshima and Nagasaki, Japan.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Letters, documents, photographs, drawings, and models (signed by Paul Tibbets) related to the atomic bomb and its use in Hiroshima and Nagasaki, Japan.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Rudin, Stephen,; Enola Gay (Bomber).
Subjects:
Atomic bomb.
Places:
Hiroshima-shi (Japan) -- History -- Bombardment, 1945.; Nagasaki-shi (Japan) -- History -- Bombardment, 1945.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Letters and Documents
Series II. Photographs
Series III. Blueprints and Models
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Letters and Documents
  - Ashworth, Frederick, August 9, 1945; TMS; Pages: 19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    First hand account of the atomic bomb attack on Nagasaki.
    Rudin # M-1
  - Beahan, Kermit, Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Signed Questionnaire regarding Hiroshima.
    Rudin # M-1B
  - Caron, George, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    "Hiroshima: I Saw it First". Bound booklet signed by tail gunner of the Enola Gay.
    Rudin # M-2
  - Caron, George Writer's location: Denver, CO, ALS; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Questionnaire/Interview regarding Hiroshima.
    Rudin # M-2A
  - Ferebee, Thomas W., DocS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Message of the Japanese Home Service after Hiroshima, signed by Ferebee.
    Rudin # M-3
  - Jeppson, Morris Addressee: George, ALS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Explanation in his role on the Enola Gay mission.
    Rudin # M-3A
  - Jeppson, Morris Addressee: Ronald Kelluern, March 20, 2006; TLS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Jeppson's personal thoughts about the Hiroshima mission.
    Rudin # M-4
  - Jeppson, Morris Addressee: Michael Writer's location:, January 15, 2009; ALS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    "No second wishes about Hiroshima mission - either about selection or results."
    Rudin # M-4A
  - Jeppson, Morris Addressee: Dear Sir, ALS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    If invasion failed, "Would more atomic bombs have been used in attempts to finally defeat Japan?"
    Rudin # M-5
  - Jeppson, Morris Addressee: Dear Bill, ALS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Reflecting on the Hiroshima mission.
    Rudin # M-5A
  - Jeppson, Morris Addressee: Dear Sir, ALS; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Arming and releasing the Hiroshima bomb.
    Rudin # M-6
  - Jeppson, Morris Addressee: Bill Smith, June 21, 2009; ALS; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Jeppson writes a detailed response regarding the Hiroshima mission after being questioned by an admirer.
    Rudin # M-6B
  - Jeppson, Morris Addressee: Dear Sir Writer's location: Hiroshima, August 6, 1945; ALS; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Jeppson answers questions of a correspondent about the effects of the bomb on the crew and the destruction and radioactive fallout that were produced.
    Rudin # M-6C
  - Jeppson, Morris Addressee: Dear Sir Writer's location: Hiroshima, August 6, 1945; ALS; Pages: 3 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Jeppson reveals his thoughts of his mission and describes the use of the atomic bomb.
    Rudin # M-6D
  - Gallagher, Ray Addressee: Mr. Schwab Writer's location:, December 24, 1986; ALS; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Reflects on current thinking regarding the use of the atomic bomb.
    Rudin # M-7A
  - Rehl, Donald C. Addressee: Fred D. Cavinder Writer's location: Fountaintown, Indiana, July 22, 1985; TLS; Pages: 8 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Pilot of unused third atomic bomb mission justifies its use.
    Rudin # M-7
  - Sweeney, Charles Writer's location: Nagasaki, Japan, August 9, 1945; TMS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Pilot describes shock waves and fireball resulting from the atomic bomb dropped on Nagasaki.
    Rudin # M-8
  - Sweeney, Charles Addressee: Mr. Norman, April 9, 1986; ALS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Pilot clarifies a historical mistake about his Nagasaki mission - Which plane actually dropped the Nagasaki bomb.
    Rudin # M-9
  - Tibbets, Paul, August 6, 1945; Signed cards; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    "The plane was named "Enola Gay" after my mother," plus a second signature card.
    Rudin # M-10
  - Tibbets, Paul Writer's location: Columbus, Ohio, September 29, 1979; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 19A)
    Tibbets defends his President's decision to use the atomic bomb.
    Rudin # M-11
  - Tibbets, Paul Writer's location: New York, August 7, 1945; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Souvenir facsimile of the front page of the New York Times announcing the bombing of Hiroshima, signed by Paul Tibbets.
    Rudin # M-12
  - Tibbets, Paul, February 2002; Pages: 1 (Folder 1)
    Limited edition souvenir typescript (21/24) recalling dropping of the bomb on Hiroshima.
    Rudin # M-14
  - Tibbets, Paul, July 24, 2004; Typescript; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Reflections on Hiroshima plus signed color photo of Enola Gay.
    Rudin # M-13
  - Tibbets, Paul, August 14, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 21A)
    Two identical first day covers, signed by tibbets, with a cachet and stamp. In addition, a full sheet of 36 commemorative stamps.
    Rudin # M-15B
  - Newsmap issued during WWII, a summary of events during the week the Atomic Bomb was dropped on Hiroshima, July-August, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 21B)
    Rudin # M-15C
  - Tibbets, Paul Addressee: General Carl Spaatz Writer's location: Washington, D.C., July 25, 1945; DocS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Reproduction of DS giving the directive to proceed with bombing of Japan, weather permitting. Two Copies.
    Rudin # M-17 and 18
  - Tibbets, Paul Addressee: Mayor Timothy Curtin Writer's location: UN, NY and Columbus, Ohio, October 23, 1964 and July 24, 1980; TLS and envelope; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    First Day Cover signed by Tibbets and Mitsuo Fuchida, the Japanese commander who led the first wave of attack on Pearl Harbor. Letter regarding Tibbets' second thoughts on dropping the bomb.
    Rudin # M-19
  - Tibbets, Paul, Typescript; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Interview with USA Today about the dropping of the atom bomb.
    Rudin # M-20
  - Van Kirk, Theodore Addressee: Dear Sir, ALS; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Letter concerning the bombing of Hiroshima.
    Rudin # M-22
  - Van Kirk, Theodore, TMS; Pages: 9 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Manuscript covering every aspect of the mission over Hiroshima.
    Rudin # M-23
  - Van Kirk, Theodore Addressee: Dear Max Writer's location:, ALS; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Response to two questions - If Van Kirk agreed to the use of the atomic bomb; and his position on civilian casualties.
    Rudin # M-24
  - Van Kirk, Theodore, Typescript; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Signed statement entitled "Atomic Bomb Explosion Over Hiroshima".
    Rudin # M-25
  - Van Kirk, Theodore, ALS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Rudin # M-26
  - Van Kirk, Theodore, TLS; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Description of the training and preparation for dropping the first atomic bomb over Hiroshima.
    Rudin # M-27
  - Van Kirk, Theodore, TLS; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Letter with important details of the dropping of the bomb plus hand-drawn illustration.
    Rudin # M-28
  - Ferebee, Brown Addressee: Writer's location: Tulsa, OK, November 1, 1990; Typescript, signed; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Mary Babrick Brown donated her hair to be used in a bomb aiming device known as the "Norden Bomb Sight".
    Rudin # M-28A
  - Tibbets, Beser, Diagram, signed; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Photocopy of the Enola Gay's escape maneuver after dropping the bomb.
    Rudin # M-29
  - Tibbets, Ferebee Location: Hiroshima, DocS; Pages: 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Signed blast damage map of Hiroshima.
    Rudin # M-30
  - Tibbets, Ferebee, 1914, 1945; Manuscript signed (Box 2, Folder 2)
    White House Press Release on Hiroshima, "The World Set Free" HG Wells excerpt, the effects of atomic bombs on Hiroshima and Nagasaki. Signed.
    Rudin # M-31
  - Beser, Caron, Ferebee, Van Kirk, August 6, 1969; DocS; Pages: 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    The City of Hiroshima Peace Declaration read by Mayor Setsuo Yamada. Signed by four members of the Enola Gay crew.
    Rudin # M-31A
  - "Operation Crossroads" flown envelope, Envelope (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Envelope carried in Army Air Force B-29 "Dave's Dream" for Atomic Bomb Test #1. With nine signatures.
    Rudin # M-40A
  - Bikini Atoll A-Bomb, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Log of observers "Panamint Parade", three newspaper articles.
    Rudin # M-40
  - Olivi, Besser, Albury, Kuharek, Gallagher, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Reproduction of General Order Number 71 awarding the Distinguished Flying Cross to the crew of Bockscar for their mission over Nagasaki.
    Rudin # M-38
- Series II. Photographs
  - Jeppson, Morris, August 6, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Photo of destruction after the atomic bomb was dropped, with inscription by Morris Jeppson.
    Rudin # M-5B
  - Tibbets, Paul (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Signed photograph of Tibbets after landing the Enola Gay and accomplishing Hiroshima bomb mission. Shown receiving Distinguished Service Cross from General Carl Spaatz.
    Rudin # M-15
  - Tibbets, Paul, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 7A)
    Three items: First day of non-issue cover, signed photo of Tibbets being decorated after Hiroshima, Photo of Japanese surrender signed by Tibbets
    Rudin # M-15A
  - Tibbets, Paul (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Signed 8.5"x11" photo of Enola Gay by Paul Tibbets. (Over bomb pit) Also included is a letter explaining the "R" tail marking.
    Rudin # M-16
  - Van Kirk, Theodore (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Signed and inscribed photo of Enola Gay.
    Rudin # M-29A
  - Van Kirk, Theodore (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Signed photo of Enola Gay coming in for a landing.
    Rudin # M-29B
  - Tibbets, Van Kirk, Ferebee, August 6, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Signed photo of mushroom cloud over Hiroshima signed by Tibbets, Van Kirk and Ferebee. Two different photos.
    Rudin # M-33 and 34
  - Tibbets, Van Kirk, Ferebee (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Enola Gay signed photo by Tibbets, Van Kirk and Ferebee.
    Rudin # M-35
  - Tibbets, Van Kirk, Ferebee, August 6, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Signed photo of Hiroshima mushroom cloud signed by Tibbets, Van Kirk and Ferebee. Plus signed photo of the crew members - Tibbets, Van Kirk and Ferebee.
    Rudin # M-35A
  - Tibbetts, Jeppson, Sweeney, Ashworth (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Signed photo with descriptions of the two atom bombs that were dropped on Japan. Signed by Tibbets, Jeppson, Sweeney, and Ashworth.
    Rudin # M-36
  - Tibbets, Van Kirk, Jeppson, Ferebee, Nelson, Winter 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Aerial view of Hiroshima in the winter of 1945-46. Signed in blue felt tip by crew members
    Rudin # M-36B
  - Van Kirk, Theodore, August 6, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 15A)
    Aerial photo of Hiroshima after the destruction of the A-bomb with inscription by Van Kirk.
    Rudin # M-36C
  - Tibbets, Van Kirk, Ferebee, Jeppson, Nelson, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Signed Enola Gay photo, Tibbets being decorated after mission, and bomber signed by Tibbets.
    Rudin # M-37
  - Olivi, Sweeney, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Photo of Bockscar on tarmac signed by Olivi and Sweeney.
    Rudin # M-38A
  - Photographs, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Lot of 15 photos after the dropping of the atomic bomb on Hiroshima. Images contain devastated scenery and buildings, as well as photos of survivors and military personnel. (See captions on verso on some of the photos).
    Rudin # M-39
  - Photographs, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Three original wire photos: two Nagasaki bomb blast photos, Hiroshima devastation.
    Rudin # M-39A
  - Bikini Atoll Test, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    20 photographs from Operation Crossroads, the United States' 1946 nuclear bomb tests.
- Series III. Blueprints and Models
  - Blueprint of "Little Boy" Hiroshima bomb (Folder 1)
    Handwritten explanations of the components and how it works. Signed by Morris Jeppson.
    Rudin # M-6A
  - Wooden model of the B-29 Enola Gay (Box 3, 4)
    1/72 scale wooden model of the Enola Gay, signed on the wing by Tibbets. On wooden display stand and accompanied by a photo of Tibbets signing.
    Rudin # M-10A
  - Plastic model of the "Little Boy" bomb
    Cast plastic scale model of the "Little Boy" atomic bomb dropped over Hiroshima signed by Paul Tibbets.
    Rudin # M-10B
  - Blueprint of "Fat Man" Nagasaki bomb. (Folder 1)
    Handwritten explanations of the components and how it works by Van Kirk.
    Rudin # M-21
  - Navigators log (Folder 1)
    Log of the Enola Gay entirely filled out in the hand of Van Kirk.
    Rudin # M-21A
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Signed Books
Flight of the Enola Gay, by Paul Tibbets. 1989. Signed by Tibbets, Van Kirk, and Ferebee. Rudin # M-32
Return of the Enola Gay, by Paul Tibbets. 1998. Signed by Tibbets and Van Kirk. Rudin # M-32A
The Tibbets Story, by Paul Tibbets with Clair Stebbins and Harry Franken. Signed by Tibbets, Ferebee and Van Kirk. Rudin # M-32B
509th Pictorial History, by 509th Composite Group. Facsimile edition of 1945 copy. Signed by Tibbets. Rudin # M-32C
Enola Gay, by Gordon Thomas and Max Witts. 1977. Signed and inscribed by Tibbets. Rudin # M-32D